this is the final video where we discuss
Spinners as members of Clifford algebras
in the previous video we discussed how
Spinners are members of minimal left
ideals in Clifford algebras the easiest
way to get a minimal left ideal is to
find a minimal projector or item potent
element that creates a minimal left
ideal in this video we're going to talk
about nil potent Elements which are
elements that square to zero and we'll
see how nil poent can create projectors
which can then create minimal left
ideals for
us I'm also going to discuss maximally
isotropic subspaces and their
relationship to minimal left ideals
we'll see that as an isotropic Subspace
gets bigger and bigger the corresponding
ideal will get smaller and
smaller now to start this video I'm
going to talk about a concept in quantum
mechanics called creation and
annihilation
operators these operators are used to
create and Destroy particles in
multi-particle quantum mechanics and
Quantum field Theory I don't expect you
to be too familiar with this but I've
left some links in the description to
videos that discuss them in more
detail if you've ever studied the
quantum harmonic oscillator you'll know
that one way to solve for the energy
levels is to use the so-called raising
and lowering operators also called
ladder
operators these can be used to travel
between the various quantized energy
states of the
oscillator also the commutator of the
raising and lowering operators equals
1 when we upgrade to multiparticle
Quantum Mechanics we get similar
operators that allow us to create
particles and destroy or annihilate
particles and they obey a similar
commutation
relation these operator work for
particles called
bons the defining property of bons is
that multiple bons are allowed to occupy
the same Quantum State the photon is an
example of a
bozon the other main category of
particles is
ferons the defining property of Fons is
that they obey the PO Exclusion
Principle which says that two Fons
cannot exist in the same state at the
same time matter type particles like
quarks electrons and neutrinos are
examples of
Fons now let's look at the operators
related to creating and destroying
ferons so with Fons we only have two
valid States the empty State and the
full or occupied state which has a
particle in it we'll say that the
operator Alpha plus is the creation
operator that takes the empty State and
and creates a firon particle giving us
the full or occupied state so Alpha plus
acting on the empty State gives us the
full
State conversely we'll say the operator
Alpha minus is the annihilation operator
it takes the full State destroys the
firmon particle and Returns the empty
state so Alpha minus acting on the full
State gives us the empty
State now what would happen if we appli
the creation operator to the full State
creating another firon would imply we
have two firion in the same state which
is impossible so we say this is equal to
zero this zero indicates that the
probability of getting two or more Fons
in the same state is
zero similarly when we apply the
annihilation operator to the empty State
this would imply we have less than zero
particles which is impossible
so we say that this equals z as
well if we examine these rules a little
more we get some interesting
results what happens when we apply the
creation operator twice to the empty
State the first operator fills the state
and the second Operator just gives us
zero and if we apply two creation
operators to the full State we
immediately get zero as a result so
regardless of the initial State applying
the creation operator twice gives us
zero the same is true for applying the
annihilation operator twice applying two
Annihilation operators to the full State
the first one empties the state and the
second one gives zero and applying to
Annihilation operators to the empty
State gives us zero immediately so
applying to Annihilation operators
always gives
zero so both Alpha plus and Alpha minus
Square to Z we say an operator that
squares to zero is called nil
potent so both the creation and
Annihilation operators for Fons are nil
potent you might also see elements with
this property called isotropic or null
although this language is more often
used in the case of
vectors another interesting property
involves the anti commutator of alpha
minus and Alpha plus the anticommutator
is usually denoted with these curly
braces and represents adding the
products of the two operators in the
forwards and backwards
directions let's apply the anti
commutator to the empty State we
distribute and get two terms for the
first term we create on the empty state
to get full and then destroy full to get
empty again on the second term we
destroy the empty state so we get
zero overall applying the anticommutator
to the empty State just gives us the
empty State
again now let's apply the anticommutator
to the full State again we get two terms
in the first term we try creating on the
full state so we get zero in the second
term we destroy the full state to get
empty and then create to get full again
so the anticommutator
on the full State gives us the full
State what this means is that the
anticommutator of alpha minus and Alpha
plus equals 1 because whichever State we
apply it to is just returned to us
without any
changes we can also Express the nil
potent of alpha minus and Alpha Plus in
terms of anticommutator by saying that
the anticommutator of alpha minus with
itself is zero and the anticommutator of
alpha a plus with itself is
zero these three anti-commutation
relations fully describe the creation
and Annihilation operators for
Fons now what can we do with
this it turns out that the nil potent
operators we just discovered the
creation and Annihilation operators for
Fons can be used to build projectors
that give us minimal left ideals in
Clifford
algebras when we take the nil potent
elements and form their anticommutator
we see it gives one it turns out that
the two terms in the anticommutator are
orthogonal projector partners that sum
to one similar to the projectors we've
come across in the last couple
videos if you like you can pause the
video and try to prove that each of
these two elements are projectors that
is they Square to themselves but I'm
going to go ahead and prove it now
now let's take p+ which equals Alpha
minus Alpha plus and show that it
squares to itself we get a product of
four operators and we can take the inner
Alpha plus Alpha minus and notice that
it matches this term In our
anti-commutation
relation this means we can rewrite it as
1 minus Alpha minus Alpha plus after we
distribute the first term becomes Alpha
minus Alpha plus and the second term has
Alpha minus twice which immediately goes
to zero since it's nil potent so we end
up with Alpha minus Alpha plus which is
the original projector
p+ so p+ does Square to itself meaning
that p+ is a
projector we can use a similar proof to
show that P minus is a
projector you can also pause and try to
show that P plus and P minus are
orthogonal that is their product in
either direction is zero p+ * P minus
gives us Alpha plus twice in the middle
which goes to zero because it's nil
potent and in the other direction P
minus * p+ Alpha minus twice in the
middle goes to zero because it's nil
potent so using our nil potent elements
Alpha minus and Alpha plus we're able to
Define two orthogonal projectors p+ and
P minus that sum to
one before we defined projectors by
finding an element u in our Clifford
algebra that squared 2 + 1 and then
using the Formula 1 12 * 1 + U to define
a
projector but now we have an alternative
method for constructing projectors that
uses nil potent that anti- commute to
one so to some everything up we have two
nil potents Alpha minus and Alpha plus
that square to zero and also anti
commute to one we can use these nil
potents to Define projectors p+ and P
minus which Square to themselves these
projectors are orthogonal and multiply
with each other to give zero we can also
reinterpret this anti-commutation
relation to mean that the two orthogonal
projectors sum to
one so all of this so far might seem a
bit abstract we've been talking about
nil potent and projectors in abstract
terms but I haven't yet connected this
back to Clifford
algebras to get a concrete example let's
look at the SpaceTime algebra
cl13 where the basis Vector gamma T
squares 2 + 1 and the basis vectors
gamma's XY Z all square to - one and all
the basis vectors anti commute with each
other vectors in space time that point
along the directions of light beams are
called lightlike vectors and these
lightlike vectors Square to zero for
this reason we also say that lightlike
vectors are null isotropic or nil
potent a simple lightlike Vector is
gamma t plus gamma Zed it's easy to see
this Vector squares to zero the inner
terms cancel because they anticommute
and the outer terms become 1 - one which
goes to zero so this lightlike Vector
can be thought of as a nil potent
element the vector gamma T minus gamma
Zed which represents a light beam
pointing in the minus Z direction also
squares to
zero for reasons that we'll see later
I'm going to multiply both of the these
vectors by 1/ 12 this doesn't change the
fact that they're nil
potent I'm going to call these two
vectors Alpha plus and Alpha
minus we can check that the product of
these nil potent elements give
projectors we'll Define p+ as Alpha
minus * Alpha plus expanding all this
out we get 1 12 * 1 + gamma T gamma
Z this gamma T gamma Zed by Vector
squares 2 + 1 so this looks like the
projectors we're familiar with from
previous
videos we also Define p minus to be
Alpha plus * Alpha minus this gives us
the complimentary projector 1 12 * 1 -
gamma T gamma
Zed it's easy to see that when we add
these two projectors we get 1 or
equivalently the anticommutator of our
two nil potent is one
this is why we multiplied our nil potent
by a factor of 1/2 we wanted to make
sure the anticommutator gave us one
instead of
four so let's review what we've done
here we started with our SpaceTime
algebra
cl13 then we found a pair of nil potent
elements Alpha plus and Alpha minus that
anticommute 2 one we then used the
products of these nil potents to give us
project s we can now use one of these
projectors to give us a left ideal by
multiplying the entire algebra onto the
projector from the left a procedure we
talked about in the previous two
videos however we saw in the last video
that one projector in
cl13 is not enough to give us a minimal
ideal there are still smaller ideals
inside our current ideal so we need to
find another projector to make our ideal
even
smaller we can do this by finding
another pair of nil potent
elements I'm going to choose beta plus
which is 12 * I gamma x + gamma Y and
beta minus which is 1 12 * I gamma x
minus gamma
y you can go ahead and check for
yourself that these elements Square to
zero and also anti- commute to
one another important property is that
the betas an commute with the alphas so
we can swap the order of an alpha and a
beta in exchange for a negative
sign the reason this is important is
because it means projectors built from
alphas and projectors built from betas
will commute with each
other remember the reason we care about
commuting projectors is because the
product of commuting projectors is also
a
projector if we Define the projector Q
Plus and Q minus using the products of
the betas we get these projectors that
we saw in the previous
video if we multiply p+ and q+ we can
rewrite the projectors out in terms of
our Alpha and beta nil
potent we can then swap beta minus over
in exchange for two negative signs and
then swap beta plus over in exchange for
two negative
signs overall there is no sign ch change
and we've managed to swap the order of
the alphas and betas which means we've
swapped the order of our
projectors so just to make this clear
when we build projectors from pairs of
nil potents where the nil potents
between the pairs anti commute with each
other we end up with projectors that
commute with each
other now we can take our ideal produced
by p+ and multiply it onto the commuting
projector q+
this gives us an even smaller ideal
which in fact happens to be a minimal
ideal so this is where Spinners live in
the SpaceTime
algebra okay let's go over this
procedure again from the beginning and
this time I'm going to explain how this
relates to the concept of maximally
isotropic
subspaces remember the general procedure
for building Spinners is to find a pair
of nil potents that anti commute to one
then use them to build projectors then
use the projectors to project out an
ideal from our
algebra however we need to remember that
Spinners live in a minimal ideal an
ideal set in our algebra that contains
no sub ideals inside of it except for
the trivial ideal consisting of just the
zero
element let's say that we find a
projector that gives us an ideal but the
ideal is not minimal because it has a
non-trivial ideal inside of it this
means we need to continue using more and
more projectors to shrink our ideal so
that it's smaller and smaller until we
reach a minimal
ideal so let's start with our n potents
Alpha plus and Alpha minus that we've
shown here I've already said that nil
potent vectors are also called isotropic
vectors so we can think of our nil
potent Vector Alpha plus as spanning an
isotropic space which is a space where
all elements Square to zero this space
is just a line since it only has one
basis vector or more technically since
we're allowing for complex scaling
coefficients we can think of our
isotropic space as one complex
dimensional visualized as the complex
plane now if we use these nil potents to
build a projector we get an ideal but
it's not a minimal ideal so we need
another projector to make our ideal
smaller another way of saying this is
that we need to make our isotropic
Subspace bigger we need more nil potent
so that we can make more projectors so
that we can make our ideal smaller so we
introduce nil potent beta plus and beta
minus now we can take our isotropic
Subspace spanned by Alpha plus and and
expand it by including the span of beta
plus this isotropic Subspace is now two
complex
dimensional also a key property is that
the basis vectors for this space Alpha
plus and beta plus anti commute with
each other another way of saying this is
that the alpha plus and beta plus
vectors are orthogonal basis vectors
since in Clifford algebras orthogonal
vectors anti- commute with each other
remember this makes it so that the
resulting projectors commute with each
other the fact that Alpha plus and beta
plus anti- commute also ensures that
every Vector in their span is also
isotropic if we take any linear
combination of alpha plus and beta plus
and multiply it by itself the outer
terms go to zero because the vectors are
isotropic and the inner terms go to Zero
by the anti-commutation
property so we get zero overall so this
anti-commuting property of the isotropic
basis vectors ensures every Vector in
this Subspace is also isotropic hence
the name isotropic
Subspace using our expanded isotropic
Subspace we can build more projectors
which give us a smaller ideal and in
fact this smaller ideal is a minimal
ideal in
cl13
so it turns out that the isotropic
Subspace we've built here is a maximally
isotropic Subspace it's the largest
possible isotropic Subspace we can build
inside this Clifford
algebra so the rule is we start with nil
potents from an isotropic Subspace in
our Clifford algebra then use them to
build a projector to get an ideal if we
need a smaller ideal we expand our
isotropic Subspace to get another
projector to get a smaller ideal the
larger our isotropic Subspace the
smaller our ideal we keep expanding our
isotropic Subspace until we reach a
maximally isotropic Subspace which means
we can produce the smallest possible
ideal which is a minimal left
ideal so the key idea from this video is
in order to build minimal left ideals
where Spinners live we need to build
projectors using nil potence from a
maximally isotropic
Subspace so let's generalize this
procedure to a general Clifford algebra
let's start with
cn0 with complex coefficients where all
our basis vectors Square 2 + 1 Let's
assume that we have an even number of
basis vectors we can build nil potent by
grouping the basis vectors into pairs
the elements 12 * Sigma 1+ plus I Sigma
2 and 12 * Sigma 1us I Sigma 2 are nil
potents that anti- commute to one we can
build more nil potent pairs that anti-c
commute to one using similar formulas
making sure that no basis vectors are
used in more than one
pair note that all the alpha pluses and
Alpha minuses from different pairs anti-
commute with each other this means that
all the alphas from different pairs are
mutually orthogonal with each other this
means that the set of alpha pluses form
an orthogonal basis for our maximally
isotropic
Subspace we use all our nil potents to
build
projectors and we multiply all our
projectors together to get a minimal
projector which gives us a minimal left
ideal which is where Spinners
live now what about clpq with complex
coefficients
here vectors can square to + one or
minus1 so how do we build nil potent
here our nil potent will always take
this form as 1/2 times the sum or
difference of two
vectors the first Vector must Square to
+ one and the second Vector must Square
to
minus1 so if both vectors Square 2 + 1
then the second Vector needs a factor of
the complex I so it squares to
-1 if the first Vector squares 2 + 1 and
the second Vector squares 2 minus1 we
can just leave them as they are with no
complex
factors if the first Vector squares to
minus one and the second Vector squares
2 + 1 then both vectors need factors of
the complex
I and if both vectors Square 2 minus one
then the first Vector needs a factor of
the complex
I other than that the steps are the
exact same build a maximally isotropic
Subspace from the nil potent use the nil
potent to build a minimal projector and
use the projector to get a minimal left
ideal where Spinners
live now note that this procedure only
works in Clifford algebras where P plus
Q is an even number because we need an
even number of basis vectors to build
pairs of nil potent
elements let's finish off this video
with a concrete example of building
Spinners in
cl20 with complex
coefficients cl20 is not a very big
Clifford algebra it has one scaler two
vectors and one B Vector we can scale by
complex coefficients so you can think of
this as four complex dimensional or
eight real
dimensional this actually ends up being
equivalent to cl30 with real coefficient
under this
isomorphism we can build our pair of nil
potents that anti- commute to one as
follows we can then use the nil potence
to build these
projectors when we apply our four
complex dimensional algebra onto p12
plus from the left we end up with a
minimal left ideal that is two complex
dimensional it is spanned by our
projector and sigma 1 times our
projector
so we can build Spinners as linear
combinations with these two basis
elements also notice that we can take
Sigma 1 * the projector and use a bunch
of algebra to rewrite it as Alpha plus *
the projector this is an equivalent way
of writing our spinner
components this gives us a two component
spinner in
c20c you might notice that the first
component looks a little bit like an
empty firon State and the second
component looks a bit like a filled Fon
State Cole Fury makes note of this fact
as well in her playlist when she refers
to this as a fox
space however at this point I don't see
any reason to literally view these
components as filled and empty States
this mathematical analy with fermion is
just something I used to help us
understand nil potent better as far as
I'm concerned these are just two basis
Spinners used to make a spinner in
cl20 they're not actual filled or empty
States if we go to higher Dimensions the
basis elements for Spinners will include
all possible combinations of nil potent
acting on the
projector so this is the last video that
discusses Spinners in terms of Clifford
algebras I realize a lot of the concepts
in the last few videos have been very
abstract but learning them is helpful
for working with spinners in arbitrary
Dimensions hopefully these videos will
make it easier to understand textbooks
and papers that talk about minimal left
ideals and maximally isotropic
subspaces you can also check out this
playlist by Cole Fury which helped me
understand how nil potent can be used to
build projectors and how projectors give
us Spinners I've linked it in the
descript
deson in the next video we'll start
talking about how Le groups and Lee
algebras relate to
spinners